Guide to the Vassar College Coordinating Council for War Activities Records, 1942-1945
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Vassar College Coordinating Council for War Activities Records
1942-1945
Vassar College. Coordinating Council for War Activities
2.4 cubic feet (5 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, government pamphlets, reports, posters, memoranda, financial records, brochures, and other items relating to women's involvement in World War II activities including the armed services, Red Cross work, college war councils, and raising bonds.
Administrative History
The Vassar College Coordinating Council for War Activities (War Council) was formed in October 1942 to formulate and guide student initiatives in support of the U.S. war effort during World War II. Originating in the earlier Defense Council (established in the fall of 1941), the War Council was established formally through an act of the college's Legislative Assembly. The Council included a faculty advisory panel that helped students develop their academic programs in preparation for war service. The Council oversaw activities in several areas, including refugee relief, enforcing blackouts, and civilian volunteer efforts. The Council also took part in curriculum development, helping to devise courses that taught skills, such as first aid and office management, directly relevant to the war effort. The Council continued its work until the fall of 1943, when it was replaced by the War Service Committee.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, government pamphlets, reports, posters, memoranda, financial records, brochures, and other items relating to women's involvement in World War II activities including the armed services, Red Cross work, college war councils, and raising bonds.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Henry Noble MacCracken Papers
War Service Committee Records
Subject Headings
Organizations:
American Red Cross; Vassar College--History
Subjects:
War--Women's work; World War, 1939-1945--War work--Red Cross
Document Types:
Correspondence; Posters; Printed ephemera
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Special Programs and Projects
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, April 2007. Updated by Mark Seidl, November 2011, and Emma Gronbeck, January 2024.
Series List
- Series I. Subject Files, 1942-1943; (Boxes 1-3)
  The material in this series documents the founding, administration, and activities of the Coordinating War Council. Arranged alphabetically.
- Series II. Posters, circa 1942-1945; (Boxes 4-5)
  This series consists of posters addressing a broad range of topics, including support for U.S. allies, military and civilian service, resource conservation, and investment in war bonds.
Container List
- Series I. Subject Files
  - Air Raid Wardens, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.1)
  - Alumnae: Dealings, undated (Folder 1.2)
  - American Friends Service Committee, undated (Folder 1.3)
  - Athletic Associations, undated (Folder 1.4)
  - British War Relief Society, undated (Folder 1.5)
  - Business Office Administration - First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.6)
  - Canteen - Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.7)
  - Catherine St. Center - Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.8)
  - Child Care Aides, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.9)
  - China, undated (Folder 1.10)
  - Civilian Defense Corps Pamphlets, undated (Folder 1.11)
  - Civilian Volunteer Activities: Programs-Reports, undated (Folder 1.12)
  - Community Church: Information, Program, undated (Folder 1.13)
  - Completed Courses, First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.14)
  - Coordinating Council for War Activities-Notes, undated (Folder 1.15)
  - Correspondence: Students Association and Intra-college, undated (Folder 1.16)
  - Correspondence: With Outside Agencies, undated (Folder 1.17)
  - Curricular Courses, Department Reports, undated (Folder 1.18)
  - Curriculum Committee and New Courses, 1943 (Folder 1.19)
  - Danish Fundamental Gymnastics, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.20)
  - Debate Society, undated (Folder 1.21)
  - Drama Department, undated (Folder 1.22)
  - Drafting and Blue Print Reading, Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.23)
  - Emergency Relief Drive, undated (Folder 1.24)
  - Emergency Relief Drive, undated (Folder 1.25)
  - Emergency Relief Drive - Pledges, undated (Folder 1.26)
  - Emergency Fund Drive, undated (Folder 1.27)
  - Faculty Advisory Panel War Service, undated (Folder 1.28)
  - Fair Club, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.29)
  - Films, undated (Folder 1.30)
  - Financial and Administrative Documents, undated (Folder 1.31)
  - First Aid, All sections, First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.32)
  - First Aid: All sections, Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.33)
  - First Aid (Advanced), Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.34)
  - Free French, undated (Folder 1.35)
  - Geology: CSMWT, Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.36)
  - Greece, undated (Folder 1.37)
  - Health Programs, undated (Folder 1.38)
  - Home Nursing, undated (Folder 1.39)
  - Home Nursing: All Sections, Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.40)
  - International Student Service, undated (Folder 1.41)
  - Inventory - War Office, undated (Folder 1.42)
  - Jobs - War - Women, undated (Folder 1.43)
  - Key Center Finance, undated (Folder 1.44)
  - Krautheimer and Emergency Rescue Committee, undated (Folder 1.45)
  - Lincoln Center, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.46)
  - Miscellaneous Committees, undated (Folder 1.47)
  - Music in Wartime, undated (Folder 1.48)
  - News Clippings, undated (Folder 1.49)
  - Nutrition, First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.50)
  - Office Practice Training, First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 1.51)
  - Office of Price Administration Pamphlets: Consumer in War, undated (Folder 2.1)
  - Pamphlet, undated (Folder 2.2)
  - Pamphlet, undated (Folder 2.3)
  - Pamphlets, undated (Folder 2.4)
  - Post War Planning, undated (Folder 2.5)
  - Presidential Orders, etc., undated (Folder 2.6)
  - LISTS: Public Administration, First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.7)
  - Radio Workshop, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.8)
  - LISTS: Recreational Leadership, First Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.9)
  - Recreational Leadership, Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.10)
  - Red Cross, undated (Folder 2.11)
  - Courses: Red Cross Information, undated (Folder 2.12)
  - Refugees, undated (Folder 2.13)
  - Reports and Lists, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.14)
  - Requisition Forms, undated (Folder 2.15)
  - Russia, undated (Folder 2.16)
  - Salvage, undated (Folder 2.17)
  - Sheet Music, undated (Folder 2.18)
  - Social Consciousness on Women's Campuses, undated (Folder 2.19)
  - Social Museum, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.20)
  - Social Welfare Aides, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.21)
  - Statistics, undated (Folder 2.22)
  - Suggestions for Second Semester, 1942-1943 (Folder 2.23)
  - Teaching, undated (Folder 2.24)
  - Tyron, K. - Personal, undated (Folder 2.25)
  - Typing, undated (Folder 2.26)
  - Typewriting, undated (Folder 3.1)
  - United Service Organizations, undated (Folder 3.2)
  - United Service Organization (U.S.O.), undated (Folder 3.3)
  - Volunteer Land Corps, undated (Folder 3.4)
  - Volunteer Workers, (Poughkeepsie Ration Board Office), undated (Folder 3.5)
  - War Chest: Articles of Agreement, undated (Folder 3.6)
  - War Council Accounts, undated (Folder 3.7)
  - War Council: Accumulations of operation, 1942-1943 (Folder 3.8)
  - War Council: History and Structure, 1942-1943 (Folder 3.9)
  - War Council: Organization Publications, undated (Folder 3.10)
  - War Savings Bonds - Stamps, undated (Folder 3.11)
  - War Service Programs Master List, 1942-1943 (Folder 3.12)
  - Women Accepted for Volunteer Emergency Service (WAVES), Women's Army Auxiliary Corps (WAACS), United States Coast Guard Women's Reserve (SPARS), etc., undated (Folder 3.13)
  - World Student Service Fund, undated (Folder 3.14)
  - World Student Service Fund, undated (Folder 3.15)
- Series II. Posters
  - Posters, circa 1942-1945; (48 folders) (Box 4)
  - Poster, circa 1942-1945; (1 folder) (Box 5)